marriott.com 2013-06-05

# Marriott Online Privacy Policy | Hotel Privacy Policy Information

This Statement was last updated on **November 18, 2011** , to describe the how the privacy statement applies to all of the information we obtain from you and to update the privacy statement with respect to Marriott’s Authorized Licensees, franchisees and certain other commercial partners set out below.

###  Browsing

This Web site does not collect personally identifiable information when you browse this Web site and request pages from our servers unless you provide it to us. This means that we will not know your name, your email address, or any other personally identifiable information just because you browse the Web site unless you:

  * access the Web site from a link in an email that we sent;
  * are a Marriott or Ritz-Carlton Rewards member or have created a profile and you either log-in to your account or choose to be remembered via your cookie, including on your web-enabled mobile device.

In these cases we will know who you are based on the information you previously supplied to us. When you request a page from our Web site, our servers log the information provided in the HTTP request header including the IP number, the time of the request, the URL of your request and other information that is provided in the HTTP header. We collect the HTTP request header information in order to make our Web sites function correctly and provide you the functionality that you see on this Web site. We also use this information to personalize content presented to you, better understand how visitors use our Web site and how we can better tune it, its contents, and functionality to meet your needs.  

###  Information We Collect and How We Use It

When we need to collect personally identifiable information from you to provide you with a particular service, we will ask you to voluntarily supply us with the information we need. For example, if you would like to make a reservation at one of our hotels, we will ask you for information such as name, address, telephone number, email address, credit card number, Marriott or Ritz-Carlton Rewards number (if applicable) and room preference to process your reservation. We will use your email address to send a confirmation and, if necessary, might use the other information to contact you for help in processing the reservation. We will also use your contact information to:

  1. send you a pre-arrival message summarizing your confirmation details and providing other information about the area and the hotel;
  2. notify you about special offers and promotions as described in this privacy statement; as well as
  3. send you periodic satisfaction or market research surveys.

You can opt out of marketing communications at any time. You can also opt out of Marriott research surveys. The same types of information would be requested to complete a gift certificate purchase, register for a Marriott or Ritz-Carlton Rewards promotion, enter a sweepstakes or online game, to enroll in the Marriott/Ritz-Carlton Rewards program or to redeem Marriott or Ritz-Carlton Rewards points. On occasion, we use third parties to provide us with additional contact information about you given the information you provided to us directly. For example, if we know your name and postal address, we may use a third party to provide us with your email address. We would then use this information for market analysis and marketing purposes.

Occasionally, you may be requested to provide personally identifiable information about others to us (for example, the name, address and contact details of your travel companion). In such cases, we rely on you to obtain that other persons' consent for disclosing their information to us and inform that other persons about us, how we will use the information and our contact details for any queries.  

###  Children’s Privacy

This Web site is not intended for children and we do not knowingly solicit or collect personally identifiable information from children. We do present information regarding The Marriott Kids program on this site for the reference of adults that are interested in activities at our locations for children.

###  Reservations

The personally identifiable information you provide to us for making a reservation is made available to the applicable hotel for the purpose of meeting your reservation request. After making a reservation or completing your stay at a Marriott or Ritz-Carlton hotel, unless you tell us otherwise, the information you provide will be used by us and our Authorized Licensees for marketing of Marriott and Ritz–Carlton Hotel hotels and certain other Marriott-branded products. Marriott and Ritz-Carlton may use the services of third-party mail houses for the sole purpose of mailing materials.

After your stay we retain your personally identifiable information including details of your stay, room type and accommodation type.

###  Click to Chat

To assist you in quickly accessing the information you want on this Web site, we use third party software to proactively initiate or offer online chat if it appears that you are having difficulties navigating the Web site, if we believe you would benefit from assistance to help direct you to the desired content quicker or to make you aware of other information or offers relevant to your search. It is your choice to use the online chat feature or to close the chat window. If you choose to use the online chat feature, the person that will chat with you may access your Marriott Rewards or Ritz-Carlton information and your past stay and chat history, if applicable. All information you enter via online chat may be associated to your email address and will be stored in our systems with any other information you provide and any transaction details.

###  Accessing Marriott.com from a Web-enabled Mobile Device

Currently applies to Marriott.com website only.

You can access Marriott.com from a web-enabled mobile device to find a hotel (including clicking to call the hotel) or view or cancel a reservation. In addition, you can download an application to your BlackBerry or iPhone to provide additional functionality as described below. If you desire to view or cancel a reservation you will be required to enter your Marriott Rewards account user name and password, or Marriott confirmation number and last name. No other personally identifiable information will be requested. In addition, you can make a reservation from a web-enabled device. When you make a reservation you will need to provide certain personally identifiable information such as name, email address and credit card information. You may also enroll in the Marriott Rewards program from a web-enabled device. When enrolling in Marriott Rewards you will be required to provide certain personally identifiable information such as name, email address and point earning preference.

If you have downloaded the application to your device such as a BlackBerry or iPhone you can take advantage of finding a hotel near you that is provided via Global Positioning System (GPS) technology. No personally identifiable information is retained to deliver this service. In addition, these applications will allow you to select one touch authentication if you would like to have your Marriott Rewards number and password remembered so that you do not need to enter them every time when you are using these devices to access Marriott.com. These functions are only available from the downloaded BlackBerry and iPhone application.

###  Updating Your Marriott and/or Ritz-Carlton Rewards Account Information

You can access and review, update, or deactivate your Marriott/Ritz-Carlton Rewards information online. If you deactivate your account, all information not already required and stored as a condition of membership will be deleted. Please note that Marriott or Ritz-Carlton will never send you an email requesting your password, credit card number or social security number. If you receive an email that looks like it's from Marriott, but asks you for your credit card number or social security number, it's a fraudulent email, or "phish." We recommend that you do the following:

  * Forward the email to the US Federal Trade Commission at [spam@uce.gov](mailto:spam@uce.gov) or call 1-877-FTC-HELP (1-877-382-4357) to report it. The FTC uses the spam stored in this database to pursue law enforcement actions against people who send deceptive email.
  * Delete the email.

If you believe "phishers" have gotten access to your personal or financial information, we recommend that you also do the following:

  * Change your password.
  * Contact credit reporting services (such as Experian, Callcredit and Equifax) and have a fraud alert attached to your credit report file. Please be aware that the perpetrator may attempt to use your information to establish accounts or obtain credit at other businesses in their name.

Learn more about fraudulent email or "phish" and how to protect your personal information »

###  Marriott Rewards Communications and Use of Member Information

Communications of relevant information is important to administering the Marriott/Ritz-Carlton Rewards program and providing you the opportunity to maximize the benefits of membership

We will only disclose member and customer information within the Marriott Group (defined below), to person(s) authorized by you, to Marriott’s Authorized Licensees (defined below), to other third parties set out in this policy and to Marriott’s franchisees and property owners.    

Customer information and member rewards information will be used for the following purposes

Rewards Members Only:

1) in order to better service your account and preferences by keeping you informed of your account status and activities through printed or electronic statements;

2) to assess your entitlement to benefits;

3) to collect and process charges incurred by you in Marriott facilities;

4) to offer you additional products and services;

5) to provide packaged travel services and/or arrangements, such as airline tickets or rental cars

6) to administer the Marriott Rewards Credit Card. Based on your choices regarding how you wish to earn points (e.g., participating airlines and other company loyalty programs), we do need to transmit certain transaction information to these companies so that your point and transaction activity is accurately recorded; and

7) to offer Marriott- or Ritz-Carlton-branded products or services provided by Marriott third-party partners.

All Customers:

8) to send you Offers and Promotions from Marriott and its Affiliates and Authorized Licensees concerning any Marriott and Ritz-Carlton branded offers and promotions which we believe will be of interest to you including those related to the Marriott Vacation Club, Marriott and Ritz-Carlton Real Estate and the Marriott Rewards Credit Card (see further below); and

9) send periodic satisfaction or market research surveys.

Marketing communications may be via telephone, post and where applicable also by e-mail and text message.  

###  Creating an Online Password for Your Marriott Rewards Account

At your choice, you can create a password for your Marriott Rewards and Ritz Carlton Rewards account in order to view your information and manage your account online. You will be required to provide your name, email address, account number, a desired user name, desired password, and password reminder. Once you have an online Marriott/Ritz-Carlton Rewards account, you may review, correct, or delete information online. If you do not have online access to your account please notify your local Marriott Rewards Guest Services or Ritz-Carlton Guest Services office in writing to review, correct or delete information pertaining to your membership (there may be a charge as permitted by law), or to indicate your communication preferences.

###  Marriott Rewards/Chase Card Services Visa Card

Available to Marriott Rewards members only:

The Marriott Rewards Credit Card provides you with a means to earn Marriott Rewards points faster. If you chose to apply for a Marriott Rewards Credit Card you will link from this Web site to the credit card issuer’s Web site and will be required to enter certain personally identifiable information as part of the credit application process. You can refer to the credit card issuer’s privacy statement posted on their Web site to understand how the information you supply will be used. All terms and conditions of being a cardholder are dictated by the issuer of the card.

###  Securing the Transmission and Storage of Information

We treat the information you provide to us as confidential information; it is, accordingly, subject to our company's security procedures and policies regarding protection and use of confidential information. When we ask you for credit card data, it is transferred over a Secured Sockets Layer (SSL) line, provided you are using a SSL enabled browser such as Microsoft Internet Explorer or Mozilla Firefox. We also use SSL on other pages where you would enter personally identifiable information. This ensures that your information is encrypted as it travels over the Internet. This secure mode is enabled before any such information is transmitted from your computer or web-enabled device. You will know you are in secure mode when the padlock or key icon in the lower right-hand or left-hand corner of the computer screen appears in the locked position. In addition, when accessing a secure server, the first characters of the site address will change from "http" to "https."

After information reaches Marriott and/or Ritz-Carlton, it is stored on a secure server that resides behind firewalls designed to block unauthorized access from outside of Marriott. Because laws applicable to personal information vary by country, our hotels or other business operations may put in place additional measures that vary depending on the applicable legal requirements. Information collected on the Web sites covered by this privacy statement is generally processed and stored in the United States.

###  Travel Related Services

To provide you with a single source for purchasing packages that include other travel-related services such as airline tickets or rental cars, we have entered into agreements with select reputable third-party companies that aggregate inventory information from suppliers such as airlines and car rental companies or companies licensed to sell Marriott- or Ritz-Carlton-branded products. If you desire to purchase a package that is facilitated through Marriott.com or Ritzcarlton.com you will be linked to a Marriott/Ritz-Carlton-branded Web site that is hosted by the company. If you choose to purchase a package or Marriott- or Ritz-Carlton-branded vacation, it is necessary for you to provide personally identifiable information to execute the purchase. This information is then provided to the suppliers (e.g., airlines) for the purpose of fulfilling your order. We have entered into contracts with these third-party companies requiring that they secure your personally identifiable information as well as use it only to execute the transactions you request or to market Marriott- or Ritz-Carlton-branded vacation products. The same security and privacy commitments have been obtained from the suppliers. However, you should be aware that any personally identifiable information you have supplied directly to a supplier in any manner, in the past or in the future, is controlled by that supplier and is subject to their privacy statement and practices, for which Marriott has no responsibility.

###  Disclosure of Information to Third Parties

In addition to the travel-related services and required information sharing described directly above, Marriott and Ritz-Carlton does use the services of third party processors, such as market researchers, fulfillment houses, email service providers and mail houses that process mail for the Marriott Group, Marriott’s Authorized Licensees, persons authorized by you, and Marriott franchisees as well as such entities and marketing companies that provide these services for the Marriott Group, Marriott’s Authorized Licensees and Marriott franchisees. These parties are contractually prohibited from using personally identifiable information for any purpose other than for the purpose Marriott specifies. We do provide non-personally identifiable information to certain service providers for their use on an aggregated basis for the purpose of performing their contractual obligations to us.

Except as described in this paragraph and the sections above titled “Marriott Rewards Communications and Use of Customer Information” and “Travel Related Services” we do not permit the sale or transfer of personally identifiable information to entities outside of the Marriott family of companies, franchisees, Authorized Licensees and hotels and our third party service providers for any non-Marriott use without your approval.

See our list of Third Party Vendors

###  Ritz-Carlton – Gold Standard Service

As part our commitment to Gold Standard service at our Ritz-Carlton branded properties our staff members occasionally record details of guest preferences and other personal information about our guests in order to provide a more personalized experience on future visits.   This might include your meal or pillow preferences, anniversary dates or other things that make your stay more comfortable.  This information is made available to our other properties around the world.  If you wish to opt out of this program or have any preferences you would like us to make note of please let us know at any time. 

###  Cookies

Marriott Cookies

Our Website uses "cookie" technology. "Cookies" are encrypted strings of text that a Web site stores on a user's computer. Our Web site requires the use of a Cookie throughout the online reservation process. Without Cookies we will not be able to keep information you enter on multiple pages together. For example, unless Marriott.com and Ritzcarlton.com can remember the dates you used in your hotel search, we will not be able to check room availability. Cookies also enable us to customize our Web site and offerings to your needs and provide you with a better online experience on Marriott.com and Ritzcarlton.com. In addition, Cookies are used to:

  * Allow registered users to sign in without typing their email/Marriott and Ritz-Carlton Rewards number each time;
  * Measure usage of various pages on our Web site to help us make our information more pertinent to your needs and easy for you to access; and
  * Provide functionality such as online reservations, Marriott/Ritz-Carlton Rewards transactions, and other functionality that we believe would be of interest and value to you

The types of Cookies that we use are referred to as "session" Cookies and "persistent" Cookies. Session Cookies are temporary and are automatically deleted once you close your internet browser. Persistent Cookies remain on your computer hard drive until you delete them or are otherwise removed upon expiration. We do not use Cookies to ascertain any personally identifiable information about you apart from what you voluntarily provide us in your dealings with Marriott or Ritz-Carlton. Cookies do not corrupt or damage your computer, programs, or computer files.

Third Party Advertising Cookies

We use third-party advertising technology to serve ads when you visit our Web site and sites upon which we advertise. This technology uses information about your visits to this Web site and the sites upon which we advertise, (not including your name, address, or other personally identifiable information), to serve our ads to you. In the course of serving our advertisements to you, a unique third-party persistent Cookie may be placed or recognized on your browser. In addition, we use beacon gifs (see description below), provided by our ad-serving providers, to help manage our online advertising. These beacon gifs enable our ad server to recognize a browser's Cookie when a browser visits this site and to learn which banner ads bring users to our Web site and whether a reservation on Marriott.com is executed. The information our ad-serving providers and we collect through this technology is not personally identifiable but is used to create a profile which allows the ad-serving provider to serve adverts which are targeted towards you and your interests across the ad-serving network.

You may set your browser to block Cookies (consult the instructions for your particular browser on how to do this), although doing so to block Marriott cookies will adversely affect your ability to perform certain transactions, use certain functionality, and access certain content on our Web site.    

###  Pixel Tags

Marriott, Ritz-Carlton and its third-party service providers use pixel tags (also known as "clear gifs" "beacon gifs" etc.). Pixel tags are not visible to the user of the Web site and consist of a few lines of computer coding delivered with the Web page. Pixel tags are not used to collect any personally identifiable information about you apart from what you voluntarily provide us in your dealings with Marriott and Ritz-Carlton. Marriott, Ritz-Carlton and our email service provider use pixel tags to:

  * Track customer response to Marriott and Ritz-Carlton advertisements and Web site content;
  * Determine your ability to receive HTML-based email messages. Our email service provider includes a pixel tag, which they refer to as a "coded sensor" in all of the HTML-based messages sent on our behalf. The sensor activates when the email message is opened and flags the email address of the user as one that is capable of receiving HTML-based email messages. This capability helps our service provider to send the email in a format you can read. The sensor does not collect or use any other information. If you cannot receive HTML, you will not receive a functioning sensor;
  * Know how many users open an email and allow our service provider to compile aggregated statistics about an email campaign for us; and
  * Allow us to better target interactive advertising, enhance customer support and site usability, and provide offers and promotions that we believe would be of interest to you.

###  Emails about Special Offers and Promotions and Opt-Out

It is our intention is that you should only receive email communications that will be useful to you and that you want to receive. When you join Marriott and Ritz-Carlton Rewards, make a reservation, or request a copy of your hotel bill via email and provide your email address, we will periodically contact you via email and provide information about Marriott and/or Ritz-Carlton special offers and promotions that may be of interest to you (unless you opt out).  We will also give you the opportunity to receive Offers and Promotions from Marriott, its Affiliates and Authorized Licensees concerning other Marriott and Ritz-Carlton branded offers and promotions that we believe would be of interest to you including those relating to the Marriott Vacation Club, Marriott and Ritz-Carlton Real Estate and the Marriott Credit Card.

We typically use third party email service providers to send emails. These service providers are contractually prohibited from using your email address for any purpose other than to send Marriott or Ritz-Carlton related email.

We provide you the ability to define and modify your mailing preferences online at anytime including unsubscribe from all marketing communications. We maintain two email programs. You may select or modify your mailing preferences online at any time, including the option to unsubscribe from all marketing communications. You can unsubscribe from any of our email programs by visiting the unsubscribe page for either Marriott or The Ritz-Carlton . In addition, every time you receive an email, you will be provided the choice to opt-out of future emails by following the instructions provided in the email. You may also opt-out online of Marriott Rewards and The Ritz-Carlton Rewards emails online by updating your Rewards account, or sending a letter to Internet Customer Care - Unsubscribe, 1818 North 90 Street, Omaha, Nebraska 68114-1315 USA. Please allow 10 business days for us to process your opt-out.

###  eFolio

If you choose to participate in the in the eFolio program ("Program") you will receive hotel bills by email ("eFolio"). The eFolio will be sent to you over the Internet in an unsecured (unencrypted) manner and could be subject to interception by third parties.

If you are an employee of a company that participates in Marriott's eFolio Program and you enroll in the program and then use the corporate credit card that is provided to you by your employer to pay for your hotel expenses (hotel folio) at a Marriott property located in the United States, Canada, Mexico, Puerto Rico or Aruba, an extract of your hotel folio detailing the goods and services provided to you during your hotel stay (as an individual traveler, or as part of a group, meeting or event) will be transferred electronically to the credit card company or its agents, who will in turn, forward that extract to your employer to facilitate the processing and tracking of the travel related expenses of their employees.

Additionally, please be advised that your Marriott/Ritz-Carlton Rewards number, as entered on your reservation, acts as the eFolio identifier, prompting your bill to be transmitted to your email address of record. If your Marriott or Ritz-Carlton Rewards number is applied to another person's room reservation, or if you make a reservation for another person and provide your email address for that reservation that person's bill will be transmitted to your email address as well. It is your responsibility to inform that person that their bill will be emailed to you when your Marriott or Ritz-Carlton Rewards number or email address is attached to his/her reservation unless he/she makes alternative arrangements with a front desk associate during the stay.

###  Events and Meetings

If you would like to submit a request for proposal online or order a complimentary copy of our Meeting Planner brochure you will be required to provide certain personally identifiable information. All personally identifiable information you provide such as name, mailing address, email address and telephone number will be transmitted to Marriott as an email via the Internet and is not encrypted. Personally identifiable information you provide to us will be treated as confidential information and is subject to our company's security procedures and policies regarding protection and use of confidential information. Marriott will not use this information for any other purposes.

###  Vacation Club Ownership

Marriott Vacation Club (MVC) is a separate business operated by Marriott Vacations Worldwide Corporation that uses the Marriott brand under license. As set out in this Privacy Statement Marriott may share your personality identifiable information with MVC for the purpose of allowing MVC to market its products and services to you and provide you with exciting offers and promotions.

If you connect to the Marriott Vacation Club site please note that a separate privacy statement governs the use of that site (http://www.marriottvacationclub.com/general-information/full-privacy-policy.shtml).  We do not own or control Marriott Vacation Worldwide.

If you e-mail us to ask not to receive further marketing communications then MVC will also cease sending you marketing communications.  

###  Ritz-Carlton Real Estate  

Ritz-Carlton is pleased to present luxury residences in various locations. In addition, we also offer fractional ownership interests in a variety of resorts.  As set out in this Privacy Statement, Marriott and its Authorized Licensees may use customer’s personality identifiable information for the purpose of marketing Marriott and Ritz-Carlton’s luxury residences and fractional ownership interests.  If you decide to purchase either a residence or fractional ownership interest you will be provided a specific disclosure around the personally identifiable information required to complete the transaction and the uses and protection of that information.

###  Sweepstakes and Online Games

On occasion, we conduct sweepstakes and online games that entitle the winners to prizes. Each sweepstakes or online game has it own terms and conditions. Some sweepstakes and online games require you to choose to enter and for others you will be entered automatically if certain elements described in the sweepstakes or online games terms and conditions are met (e.g., making a reservation with a certain credit card). You will be informed before a transaction is executed if it will result in an automatic entry into the sweepstakes. As part of entering a sweepstakes or online games certain personally identifiable information such as name and email address will be required. We may use this information to send future communications about specials and offers. As stated in the email section of this privacy statement, every time you receive a marketing email you will be provided the choice to opt-out of future marketing emails by following the instructions provided in the email.

###  Careers at Marriott

Applies to the Marriott.com website.

Marriott uses select private label databases and tools hosted by third parties on their Web sites to collect information from individuals that wish to be considered for potential employment. Information you provide to us via these private label services is accessible and confidential to Marriott. By submitting your application and providing this information, you understand and agree that the information that you provide will be transferred to the United States and may also be transferred to additional countries, other than your country of origin, for consideration for employment.

Marriott will not use the information you provide for any purpose other than to allow you to conduct automated job searches or determine your qualifications for potential employment with Marriott. The third-party service providers located in the United States or United Kingdom are prohibited from using the information you provide for any purpose other than collecting it on our behalf.

###  Investor Relations Communications

At your choice, you can use this Web site to opt-in to email communications such as notices of upcoming events. All personally identifiable information you provide such as email address will be transmitted to Marriott Investor Relations as an email via the Internet and is not encrypted. Personally identifiable information you provide to us will be treated as confidential information and is subject to our company's security procedures and policies regarding protection and use of confidential information. Marriott will not use this information for any other purposes.

###  Other Sites

Marriott is only responsible for the privacy statement and content of this Web site and information we collect. We are not responsible for the data collection and use practices and privacy policy or the use of cookies on Web sites that you have accessed this Web site from and to the non-Marriott Web sites that you may access from this Web site.

###  Legal Issues

This is a United States Web site and is subject to laws of the United States and the State of Maryland. Marriott and Ritz-Carlton will disclose personally identifiable information without your permission when required by law, or in good faith belief that such action is necessary to investigate or protect against harmful activities to Marriott and Ritz-Carlton guests, visitors, associates, or property (including this site), or to others. As mentioned previously, laws related to personally identifiable information vary by country.

If you are a customer who resides in the State of California, you have the right to request from Marriott a list of third parties with whom we shared personally identifiable information about you for their own direct marketing purposes during the previous calendar year. Although Marriott/Ritz-Carlton does not share personally identifiable information with unrelated third parties for their own direct marketing purposes, many of our hotels, which are separately owned and operated by franchisees of Marriott, are permitted to use the personally identifiable information they receive from Marriott to market the Marriott hotels that they franchise. If you would like to request information about the franchisees that may have obtained personally identifiable information about you during the immediately preceding calendar year, please send an email to [privacy@marriott.com](mailto:privacy@marriott.com) or letter to Marriott International, Inc., 10400 Fernwood Road, Dept. 52/995.63, Bethesda, MD 20817.

In relation to personal data collected out of our Ritz-Carlton property in Dubai International Financial Centre please note that this personal data may be transferred to our other properties in the United Arab Emirates and other jurisdictions which may not be regarded as adequately protecting personal data.   When you check in at this property you expressly consent to such transfer.

###  Other Marriott Sites Within Marriott.com

Within Marriott.com are numerous other Marriott Web sites that are accessible from links within Marriott.com or via separate URLs. Namely, these Web sites are: marriottrewards.com, jwmarriotthotels.com, fairfieldinn.com, marriotthotels.com, renaissancehotels.com, residenceinn.com, springhillsuites.com, towneplace.com, towneplacesuites.com, conferencecenters.com, courtyard.com, marriottfoundation.org, careers.marriott.com, marriottnewsroom.com, marriott.com/investor and executiveresidences.com, editionhotels.com autographhotelcollection.com and ritzcarlton.com
